Pei-Shan Yen

: Linkedln

My-Website

☑:pyen2@uic.edu

 $\square: 608-335-7436$

Summary

Self-motivated, and enthusiastic with a positive attitude. 15 years of combined professional with 12 years of volunteering experience in statistical consulting, data analysis, and marketing research. Highly competent in problem-solving, communication skills, strategic planning, and interdisciplinary collaboration.

SKILLS

Software: R/Shiny/Markdown(8/3/5 yr), SAS/SAS macro (5 yrs), WinBUGS (1 yr), SPSS (12 yrs), Stata (1 yr), Minitab (2 yrs), SQL (1 yr), Latex (4 yrs), Unix/Linux (2 yr)

Statistics: Longitudinal Data Analysis, Statistical Inference and Modeling, Data Visualization, Marketing Research, Survey Methodology, Data Science

EDUCATION

University of Illinois at Chicago (UIC)

Chicago, USA

Ph.D. Candidate in Biostatistics (GPA: 4.00)

2018 - Present

- Research: Longitudinal Data Analysis, Causal Mediation Model, Neuroimaging Studies
- *Honor*: 2021 Paul Levy Memorial Scholarship. Founder and 2022 Vice President of Biostatistics Student Association (ASA Student Chapter). 2023 AbbVie Externship Fellowship.

National Chengchi University

Taipei, Taiwan

M.S. in Statistics (GPA: 3.86)

2010

- Research: An International Study of 2010 Population Census Methods
- Honor: Invited Paper to the Journal of Population Studies

University of Taipei

Taipei, Taiwan

B.S. in Mathematics (GPA: 3.55)

2005

• Honor: Ranked top 3% in the national mathematics undergraduate student competition

DOCTORAL RESEARCH

High-Dimensional Mediation Model for Multimodal Neuroimaging Data

Advisor: Dr. Dulal Bhaumik

- Developing one of the first penalized mediation models for high-dimensional data.
 - 1. Modeling: Construct the depiction of the pathway between therapeutic treatments and neurobehavioral outcome with two-modality high-dimensional human brain connectivity mediators. Brain structural and functional connectivities are measured by MRI technique.
 - 2. Feature Selection: Employ the high-dimensional sparsity and non-smoothness penalty functions incorporating temporal and spatial associations to select significant brain connectivity. Bootstrapping approach is proposed to verify the significance of connectivity.
 - 3. Prioritize False Discovery Rate (FDR): Present the multiple hypothesis testing procedure by taking into account the order of importance of brain connectivity.
 - 4. Model Validation: Evaluate and validate the proposed theoretical model using both statistical simulations and real-world data for the patients suffering from mental disorders.

Professional Experiences

Biostatistician, Eyecare Clinical Statistics

May 2022 - May 2023

Data & Statistical Sciences, AbbVie, USA

• Biostatistics Extern

Jan 2023 - May 2023

• Conducting coupla modeling to glaucoma project, performing statistical simulation study, and preparing manuscript. *Honor*: Fellowship with tuition waiver.

• Experiential Summer Intern

May 2022 - Aug 2022

- Applied copula invariance property to perform virtual patient simulation from small-size trial data with longitudinal correlated empirical composite outcomes. (Coding: R).
- Developed a new R package *copulaSim* for simulating joint distribution from small data without making a strong parametric assumption. (See Source Code)
- *Honor*: Third Place prize in student poster competition, 2022 NIC-ASA and ICSA Midwest Chapter Joint Fall Meeting.

Graduate Research Assistant

Jul 2019 - Dec 2022

Biostatistics Core, Center for Clinical and Translational Science, UIC, USA

- Participated in 20 medical research projects with physicians and researchers from UIC, Rush University, Northwestern University, and VA Office of Research and Development.
 - 1. Assisted 4 principal statisticians to provide consultation works.
 - 2. Performed statistical data analysis and tabulated customized results (Coding: SAS, R).
 - 3. Supported the preparation of 4 grant proposals, 4 manuscripts, and 2 conference abstracts.
- Developed an R Shiny app *Recruitment Tracker* to visualize all the datasets of the Research Electronic Data Capture database (REDCap). (Coding: R Shiny/JSON)(See Source Code).
 - 1. The functions include clinical trial recruitment tracking, descriptive statistical tabulated results, and interactive plots.
 - 2. Prepared the user manual and hosted 2 training sessions.

Graduate Research Assistant

Nov 2018 - Jul 2019

Department of Emergency Medicine, College of Medicine, UIC, USA

- Performed 5 statistical consulting projects for the professors/medical doctors.
- Prepared grant proposal and conference article. (Coding:R)

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Aug 2018 - May 2019

Division of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, UIC, USA

• Tutored the Graduate Courses "Biostatistics II" and "Analytic and Research Methods".

Senior Research Data Scientist, Acquisition and Loyalty Division Apr 2014 - Apr 2016 Taiwan Mobile, Taiwan (2^{nd} largest telecom company in Taiwan)

- Designed and conducted marketing analytic projects to locate and prioritize customer churn behavior. Proposed strategy options. Monitored marketing plans and sales performance.
- Led the data science team (a group of 8 data engineers & data scientists) in projects involving 7,000,000 users to predict churn behavior.
 - 1. Constructed a proprietary machine learning model to predict the risk of churn behavior (annual churn rate reduced by 3%). Proposed 3 natural language processing projects to prevent daily churn behavior by monitoring real-time user behavior (daily churn rate reduced by 28%).
 - 2. Analyzed the behavior of 800,000 long-term iPhone users, executed mystery shopper surveys, and designed promotional plans for new iPhones sales.

Senior Data Analyst, Energy Research Center

Nov 2011 - Feb 2014

NCKU Research and Development Foundation, Taiwan

(The leading institute to perform solar-heating subsidy program sponsored by Taiwan government)

- Led 7 large-scale field surveys, constructed cost-benefit analysis models, and analyzed the payback period with a team of 12 engineers in the poultry & butchery industry, hospitality industry, and schools in rural areas. Successfully motivated 5 large-scale system installations.
- Analyzed 130,000 solar heater user behavior in Taiwan. Evaluated lifetime of solar systems
 with cost-benefit analysis for the subsidy policy adjustments.
- Prepared 2 grant proposals, 3 annual reports, and 8 manuscripts for solar heater development.

Senior Data Analyst, 104 Web Survey Center

May 2010 - Apr 2011

104 Group, Taiwan (The largest human resource company in Taiwan)

• Proposed new research plans, executed 15 online survey research projects involving 2,000,000 customers and composed reports. Collaborated with clients including Philips (Healthcare), Shiseido (Cosmetics), Kanebo (Cosmetics), and Carat (Global Media & Marketing Agency).

Data Analyst, College of Commerce

Jun 2005 - Oct 2010

National Chengchi University, Taiwan (Best College of Commerce in Taiwan)

• Graduate Research Assistant, Department of Statistics Sep 2007 - Oct 2010

- 1. Provided 3 projects involving statistical consulting service and used the GeneSpring software to perform human genetic clustering for Academia Sinica.
- 2. Conducted user behavior studies to help design an innovative mobile device "ORBI" for interactive exhibitor information. The project was sponsored by IBM and HTC.
- 3. Conducted user behavior and pricing studies to help design an innovative mobile device "ORBI" for interactive exhibitor information, map guide and the exchange of digital business cards. The project was sponsored by IBM and HTC.
- 4. Led a team of 6 software engineers in project to redesign the computer-assisted telephone surveying system and added visualization and tracking functions. Retained the ownership of the newly designed product copyright.
- 5. Associated Statistician at Statistical Consulting Center: Performed 6 consulting projects for Hennessy, Farglory Construction, and researchers from local universities.

• Graduate Teaching Assistant, Department of Statistics Jan 2007 - Jun 2009

1. Tutored the Undergraduate Courses "Mathematical Statistics I&II," Sampling Survey, and "Statistical Software".

• Data Analyst, Market Survey Research Center

Jun 2005 - Aug 2007

- 1. Led a team of 26 interviewers and conducted 29 research projects.
- 2. Prepared research proposals, conducted analyses, composed reports, and offered feasible solutions to various government agencies, industries, and research institutes.

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Book

1. C.S. Yue and **P.S. Yen**. "Big data: The data wisdom and knowledge-based economics." *Tsang Hai Publishing*, Taiwan, 2016.

Journal Publications

- 1. D.K. Bhaumik, Y. Wang, **P.S. Yen**, and O.A. Ajilore. "Development of a Bayesian Multimodal Model to Detect Biomarkers in Neuroimaging Studies." *NeuroImage* (under review).
- 2. Y. Wang, **P.S. Yen**, O.A. Ajilore, and D.K. Bhaumik. "Selection of biomarkers using multimodal neuroimaging data for late-life depression." *PLUS ONE* (under review).
- 3. D.K. Bhaumik, Y.B. Song, **P.S. Yen**, and O.A. Ajilore. "Power Analysis for High Dimensional Neuroimaging Studies." *Psychiatric Annals* (Accepted).
- 4. I. Imayama, A. Gupta, P.S. Yen, Y.F. Chen, B. Keenan, R. R. Townsend, J. A. Chirinos, F. M. Weaver, D. W. Carley, S. T. Kuna, and B. Prasad. "Socioeconomic status impacts blood pressure response to positive airway pressure treatment." *Journal of Clinical Sleep Medicine*, 2021.
- 5. C.C. Li, A.K. Matthews, **P.S. Yen**, Y.F. Chen, and X.Q. Dong. "Intimate partner violence and Its Relationship with Psychological Distress Among Older Asian Americans: Results from the California Health Interview Survey." *Asian Journal of Psychiatry*, 2021.
- 6. C.C. Li, A.K. Matthews, **P.S. Yen**, Y.F. Chen, and X.Q. Dong. "The Influence of Perceived Discrimination in Healthcare Settings on Psychological Distress Among a Diverse Sample of Older Asian Americans." *Aging & Mental Health*, 2021.
- 7. P.S. Yen and K.C. Chang. "Survey and analysis of solar water heaters utilization status in Taiwan." Journal of Taiwan Energy, 2014.
- 8. C.W. Kuo, **P.S. Yen**, W.C. Chang and K.C. Chang. "The design and optical analysis of compound parabolic collector." *Procedia Engineering*, 2014.
- 9. **P.S. Yen** and C.S. Yue. "An international study of 2010 population census methods." *Journal of Population Studies*, 2010.

Conference Proceedings

- P.S. Yen. X. Gu, J. Jiao, J. Zhang. "Individual Patient Data based Copula Approach for Modeling and Simulation to Support Clinical Development Team Decision Making." NIC-ASA & ICSA Midwest Joint Fall Meeting, USA, 2022. Honor: Third Place prize in student poster competition
- 2. J. Li, K. Qin, P.B. Doshi, X.D. Zhu, P. Kotini-Shah, M. Granado, H. Kim, **P.S. Yen**, R. Gordon, H.E. Wang, and T. Hoek. "Novel Blood Biomarker Taurine and Glutamate for Early Predicting Outcomes After Out-of-hospital Cardiac Arrest." *AHA Resuscitation Science Symposium*, USA, 2020.
- 3. P. Kotini-Shah, R. Gordon, B. Karfunkle, J. Li, H. Kim, **P.S. Yen**, M. Granado, P. Doshi, H. Wang and T.Hoek. "Optic Nerve Sheath Diameter Differences by Sex, Rhythm, and Neurological Outcome After Out-of-hospital Cardiac Arrest." *AHA Resuscitation Science Symposium*, USA, 2020.
- Y.F. Wang, K. Schachtschneider, Y.H. Huang, R. Gaba, P. Nguyen, P.S. Yen, M. Sverdlov, G. Guzman, and R. Lokken. "Infiltration of T-cell subpopulations in hepatocellular carcinoma is associated with tumor size, BCLC stage, and transplant-free survival." Society of Interventional Radiology Conference, USA, 2020.
- 5. **P.S. Yen** and C.W. Kuo. "Policy for solar water heaters in Taiwan: An International Perspective." *Grand Renewable Energy*, Tokyo, Japan, 2014.
- 6. **P.S. Yen** and C.S. Yue. "An International Study of 2010 Population Census Methods." *Taiwan Demography Association Annual Meeting*, Taipei, Taiwan, 2010.
- P.S. Yen and C.S. Yue. "Feedback on Taiwan population registered system: A lesson from international experience using census techniques." Population Policy Symposium in Taipei City, Taipei, Taiwan, 2010.
- 8. **P.S. Yen** and C.S. Yue. "A study of 2010 population census methods." Taiwan Demography Association Annual Meeting, Taipei, Taiwan, 2009.
- 9. C.S. Yue and **P.S. Yen**. "A study on whether Taiwan population census could be replaced by survey via American Community Survey experience." Chinese Statistical Association Annual Meeting, Taipei, Taiwan, 2008.

Invited Talks

- 1. **P.S. Yen** and S. Konda. "Clustering Depression Data." Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University of Illinois at Chicago, Nov. 2019.
- 2. **P.S. Yen**. "Future Statistical Application- Big Data Project on Mobile Industry." Department of Mathematics, University of Taipei, Taiwan, Sep 2018.
- 3. P.S. Yen and K.C. Chang. "Analysis of solar thermal energy market in Taiwan." 2013 Solar Water Heaters Firm Conference, Bureau of Energy, Ministry of Economic Affairs, Tainan, Taiwan, Nov, 2013.
- 4. **P.S. Yen** and K.M. Chung. "Evaluation of solar water heater utilization status in Taiwan rural areas." 2013 Energy Conservation & Carbon Reduction, IC Broadcasting Company, Hsinchu, Taiwan, May, 2013.
- 5. **P.S. Yen**. "Statistical Application for Market Research." Department of Mathematics, University of Taipei, Taiwan, May, 2012.

Professional Organizations

Student Member

Jul 2017 - Present

American Statistical Association (ASA)

Student Member Oct 2018 - Present

Eastern North American Region International Biometric Society (ENAR)

Graduate Courses

- (*PhD level*) Generalized Linear Model, Multivariate Analysis, Advanced Statistical Inference, Large Sample Theory, Bayesian Methods, Missing Data, Computational Statistics.
- (MS level) Clinical Trial, Experiment Design, Longitudinal Data Analysis, Survival Analysis, Categorical Data Analysis, Health Analytics, Epidemiology, Demography, Sampling Methods, Statistical Consulting, Marketing Management, Product Management

SELECTED
DOCTORAL COURSE
PROJECTS

- Bayesian Statistics: Using Bayesian Ordinal Regression Model to Identify Suicide Risk Factors
- Missing Data: A Review of EM algorithm (EM, MCEM, SAEM)
- Computational Statistics: Developed R package MixPoiRayExp including an EM Algorithm for Finite Mixture Models
- Generalized Linear Model: A Review of Separation in Logistic Regression
- Independent Study for Linear Model: Two-Component Mix Model and Gamma Mixed Model for Estimating the Unknown True Concentration of Ground Water
- Linear Model: Linear Mixed-Effects Model for Detecting Disrupted Connectivities in Heterogeneous Data
- Health Analytics: Using Machine Learning Classification Methods and SMOTE Resampling Skills to Predict Disease Risk

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCES

Freelance Statistician & Volunteering Statistician

Jul 2006 - Oct 2022

Self-Employed, Taipei, Taiwan

- Provided statistics tutoring and consulting sessions for a total of 52 clients from various professional fields, including medical doctors, nurses, pharmaceutical scientists, researchers, students.
- Provided pro-bono statistics sessions for 7 underprivileged students in Taiwan & US.

President and Organizer of the Millennials Sector

May 2021 - Apr 2022

American Beiyinu Alumnae Foundation, Walnut, CA, USA

- Redesigned database and questionnaire to collect alumnae information to build networks. The number of alumnae members recruited increased from 328 to 1,397 within 5 months.
- Led and mentored a team of 45 in multiple projects in the analysis of the alumnae member profile, organization structure, marketing strategies, and the organization of alumnae activities, including career consultation, monthly workshops, and fund-raising activities.

Data Analyst Oct 2009 - Sep 2021

Asian Mental Health Association (AMHA), Taipei, Taiwan

(The leading Taiwanese organization that provides crisis response and mental health service)

- Resigned PTSD questionnaires for COVID-19 first responders and conducted statistical analysis for the evaluation of crisis response training courses.
- Provided data collection and study design ideas for AMHA, the Ministry of Health and Welfare
 of Taiwan, and the Red Cross Society of Taiwan. Executed 18 crisis response training for the
 disaster victims, first responders, the Army of the Republic of China, and various NGOs.
- Assisted the director of AMHA in the proposal and execution of the 2009 Typhoon Morakot
 Project to reduce the suicide rates of 247 victims. Developed a model to rank the suicidal
 tendency of victims and demonstrated statistical applications for 82 NGO directors. The
 results contributed to the initiation of a national-wide emergency plan.

Data Analyst Oct 2016 - Feb 2018

American Red Cross - Wisconsin Region, Madison, WI, USA

• Wrote weekly statistical reports for the emergency response vehicle management.

Data Analyst Jul 2013 - Jun 2014

Taipei Lifeline Association, Taipei, Taiwan

• Used 2011-2014 phone call records from national suicide prevention lifeline to perform data analysis for identifying suicide high-risk group.